MATT ALLSUP 314.308.6807 MALLSUP75@GMAIL.COM

SUMMARY

Senior business technology generalist with deep experience in Data & Analytics. A flexible, well-rounded contributor equally comfortable in diverse roles from pre-sales to programming. Responsibilities over this span include data strategy, stakeholder engagement, business acumen, combined with a wide swath of technologies. At core is advanced proficiency in SQL, and mid Python. DBT is my tech passion.

SKILLS SUMMARY

- Management Expertise: Financial Accounting, Strategy, Data Management, Data & Analytics Governance, Team Building, Career Development, Capability Development, Thought Leadership, Training, Performance Improvement
- Technical Skills: Big Data, Analytics & Reporting, Information Architecture, Data Modeling, ETL Architecture & Development, Cloud Infrastructure (Azure dominant)
- Industry Experience: SaaS Platform, Professional Services, Healthcare Provider, Payor, Financial Services,
 Telecommunications, Consumer Packaged Goods, Retail, Manufacturing

TECHNICAL SUMMARY

- Programming & Scripting: SQL, Python, Jinja, Stored Procedures
- Data Integration & ETL: DBT, Python, SSIS, Alteryx Data Prep, Informatica, DataStage, SAP, Talend
- Automation & Workflow Orchestration: DBT, Apache Airflow (DAG), AirByte, UI Path
- Data Engineering & Lakehouse: DBT, Databricks Community Edition
- Databases: Snowflake, SQL Server, Google BigQuery, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Oracle, DB2, SAP HANA/BW
- Cloud Platforms & Services: Azure (DevOps, laas), Apache ActiveMQ, AWS(S3)
- Command Line Interfaces: Linux, PowerShell, Azure CLI
- Business Intelligence & Viz: Tableau Power BI, Grafana, SAP Business Objects (Full Stack)
- Version Control & Project Management: Git, JIRA
- Data Modeling and Design: ER/Studio, Erwin, Toad Data Modeler

PROFESSIONAL HISTORY

Nomad eCommerce (Independent)

Oct 2024 - Present

Data Architect | Consultant

- Operational and Financial Data Integration (MDM), unified operational and financial data sources into a common data model, identifying 5.5% in unbilled services; Increased annual recurring revenue by 3% through metered usage reconciliations using SQL and Python; developed Postgres database objects, SQL functions, and constraints to automate workflows and ensure data integrity; delivered 14 visualizations and analyses, including Grafana dashboards to support business valuation and sale.
- Data integration and warehouse solutions: Postgres data model and data engineering, stored procedures
- BI systems: Grafana, PowerBI

Additional Experience (Proof of Concepts)

Present

- Clouds and IaaS: Azure, engineered end-to-end data pipeline on Azure Container Instances using Apache
 Airflow, automating JSON data extraction from a REST API and storage in Azure Blob Storage achieving seamless
 integration to create proof of concept.
- Twelve online courses for DBT to include .Yml based settings like data freshness, model metadata, tests, materialization strategies
- Microsoft 365 Co-Pilot Microsoft Fabric AI chatbot to enhance data preparation and SQL coding with natural language prompts, utilizing prompt engineering for training proof of concept
- Built and deployed a custom Docker image via Azure Container Registry, embedding azure-storage-blob and requests libraries, and managed persistent DAG storage with Azure File Shares to create proof of concept.
- Advanced transformations and feature engineering implement in Pandas, to pivot Snowflake data to prepare the data for an Auto ML regression model for proof of concept. To demonstrate hashing capabilities using libraries like hashlib for de-identification to Snowflake.
- Databases: Databricks, Snowflake, Postgres, Google Big Query

MATT ALLSUP 314.308.6807 MALLSUP75@GMAIL.COM

- APIs: Python extractor with Python Airflows Operations
- Online Certificates: DBT Fundamentals, and 80% complete on DBT Analytics Engineering Certified Developer;
 SQL Advanced on HackerRank; Databricks Fundamentals, Databricks for Data Engineers

Antage Decision Source Inc

Mar 2021 - Sep 2024

Data Architect | Consultant (Full Time)

- Data Integration and warehouse solutions: Alteryx, SSIS, SSMS, and stored procedures in data engineering capacity
- BI systems: Tableau, PowerBI, in Business Intelligence solutions
- Databases: MS Sql Server, Snowflake, PostgreSQL, MySQL in data storage and management solutions
- Clouds and laaS: Azure, AWS in infrastructure solutions; with emphasis on Azure w/ majority of clients
- Data Wrangling: Python Pandas for Data Manipulation, custom APIs: Python extractor (team)
- Lead teams of 4-10 resources in delivery to meet client goals
- Strategic Assessments & Roadmaps: Led technology landscape assessments for six clients, (of note: @Ingram Barge, @San Francisco Health Partners, @SEIU Benefits Group, @Kent Corp) delivering gap analyses and multiyear roadmaps aligned with business goals. Created detailed documentation to drive stakeholder alignment and informed decision-making.
- Conducted in-depth evaluations of technology environments, identifying key data sources, and analyzing their integration within business processes, systems, and networks to drive efficiency and uncover optimization opportunities.
- Created detailed diagrams, reference documents, and white papers to illustrate the current state of technology infrastructure, facilitating stakeholder alignment and informed decision-making.

Amitech Solutions May 2019 – Mar 2021

Senior Consultant and Delivery Lead (Full Time)

Provide strategic advisory to client organizations, delivering data and automation solutions that streamline business processes, enhance decision-making, and improve patient care and healthcare experiences.

- Worked with UiPath bots and automation frameworks (Revenue Cycle, Invoice Processing, Care Management, Provider Credentialing)
- Contributed to automation assessments (billable, pre-sales)
- Conducted needs analysis to identify automation opportunities, define value
- Worked on process discovery and automation feasibility studies
- @SSM Healthcare, provided Data Integration and warehouse solutions: SAP HANA, SSIS, and stored procedures
 in data engineering capacity
- BI systems: Tableau, PowerBI, SAP Business Objects in Business Intelligence solutions
- Databases: MS Sql Server, MS Synapse, SAP HANA in data storage and management solutions
- Clouds and laaS: Azure, Azure Data Factory
- Assessments as Data Warehouse Architect included gap analysis, current state capabilities and future roadmap for two organizations: @Wellspan Health System, @DeltaDental of Arkansas
- Client engagement and customer success experience, translating business needs into actionable solutions.
- Cross-functional collaboration, working with stakeholders from Finance, Operations, Sales, and IT.
- Leadership & mentoring: Led teams of developers and consultants, provided coaching in Agile principles, and mentored in data modeling and best practices.
- Pre-sales & business development: Contributed to statements of work (SOWs), pre-sales calls, and risk/opportunity identification.
- Communication & presentation skills: Conducted interviews, authored presentations, and guided incoming @SSM Healthcare leadership.

DIGR UnEarthing Data

April 2017 - May 2019

Director Data Integration (Independent)

Consultant @Sheer Logistics architected and developed EDI, ETL, Data Warehouse integrations, as well as Tier
 3 support for Data Visualization platform in Tableau.

MATT ALLSUP 314.308.6807 MALLSUP75@GMAIL.COM

- Tableau Developer develop cross tab reports, visualizations, and dashboards in tableau desktop. Also functioned as Tableau Server Administrator - supported Windows server environment to Tableau server including extract performance and data source tuning.
- Talend Developer performed end-to-end data integration and execution service including 45 ETL jobs working with SAP IDOC, XML, EDI, and flat files for supply chain inbound/outbound order integration. Utilized Talend data mapper (MuleSoft module).
- Solution Architect stand up Apache ActiveMQ message broker and leverage as input file source.
- Consultant @Reinsurance Group of America (RGA) performed data process and technology assessment for improvement to period close process for multi-currency financial allocation models.

Independent Practitioner

July 2012 - March 2017

Consultant

Contracted with Daugherty Business Solutions, Amitech Solutions, et al.

- Led Business Intelligence Architect @Arch Coal staffed and lead a team of up to 12 (FTE & contract) resources and interacted regularly with business senior team on strategy.
- AB InBev, to design and implement data integration architecture for wholesaler KPI reporting, working with IBM DataStage and Tivoli Workload Scheduler. Took on a variety of tasks from designing Business Objects universes to developing ETL processes, ensuring successful project delivery.
- Monsanto, to implement data integration solutions, managing external data sources into the Teradata environment and developing both physical and logical data models using Erwin and created proof-of-concept scripts using Python for data transformations and assisted with building visualizations using Tibco Spotfire as part of the Dicamba project.
- Wellmont Health System, data team, by developing SQL Server data warehouse solutions and mentoring staff on data modeling. Designed and built a semantic layer for metrics reporting from Clarity and EDW environments.
 Business Objects universe and report development.
- @BJC Healthcare, coreAnalytics project by analyzing and integrating data from 13 facilities. Worked with DB2, writing SQL scripts, mapping data sources, compliance with standard taxonomies like RxNORM and ICD-10.
- Express Scripts, Contributed to the Teradata data modeling and ETL development for internal and external reporting needs, while also converting legacy BI dashboards from Xcelsius to Tableau; data integration using Teradata BTEQ scripts
- Nestle Purina Pet Care, Worked with Business Objects and SAP BW to architect data models and develop reports, providing hands-on support to Oracle, SQL Server, and MS Access environments as needed and administered the Business Objects platform, collaborating with both IT and business teams to resolve data challenges and streamline reporting processes.

Arch Coal April 2010 - July 2012

Lead Business Intelligence Architect (Full Time)

- Led Business Intelligence Architect @Arch Coal staffed and lead a team of up to 12 (FTE & contract) resources and interacted regularly with business senior team on strategy.
- As a program manager, scope projects and calculate value in cost savings and revenue generation.
- Developed logical and physical data models, queries and reports, schedules, work processes, and maintenance procedures.
- Scoping and design of pre-fetched SAP Business Objects Explorer info space to assist in management of \$182 million in stock on hand while providing a single source of the truth.
- Develop and co-manage BI training, documentation, and ITIL type help desk capabilities.
- 24/7 support of ODS and EDW data feeds, Business Objects application and Web server stack.

EDUCATION

Bachelor of Science Degree in Accounting, Maryville University